Many decades ago, a famous scientist by
the name of Dr. Linus Pauling suggested
that vitamin C, the same stuff that's
found in citrus, berries, peppers, and
many more foods, may be a treatment for
cancer. Now, the idea was tested a few
times back in the '70s and '80s, but
found no effect, and the idea lost some
of its appeal. But, recently, more
studies have looked into the effects of
vitamin C on cancer, and some
fascinating discoveries have been made.
Just this year, a big study released
reigniting the possibility that there
may be some merit to the idea again. So,
what does vitamin C do to cancer, and
why are studies now finding some
evidence in favor of vitamin C when
previous studies didn't? In this big
study that I alluded to, researchers
were interested in figuring out if
certain types of lung cancer called
LKB1-deficient
lung cancer was especially prone to
dying off when exposed to vitamin C.
Now, the reason that they suspected this
type of lung cancer could be susceptible
is because this deficiency, the enzyme
LKB1, leads to cancer cells to produce a
lot more reactive oxygen species. These
are damaging molecules that stress the
cell. So, when vitamin C, called
ascorbic acid here, was applied to the
LKB1 lung cancer cells, there was a
significant uptick in the production of
these damaging reactive oxygen species,
seen with the higher bars, especially
the red one on the far right. This
indicates that lung cancer missing the
LKB1 enzyme experienced more damage when
exposed to vitamin C. So, then, when we
give vitamin C, ascorbic acid, to
animals with these lung cancers, do they
live longer? Does the cancer actually
struggle? The answer is an odd sort of,
because we see here tumor size. If the
lines go up, that's a greater tumor
size, not a good thing. Notice how most
of the lines go up similarly, including
the ascorbic acid condition.
That means that ascorbic acid is
ineffective at controlling this cancer.
Or is it?
There is an instance where ascorbic
acid, again, that's vitamin C, does lead
to significant effects against cancer.
See that red line? It's certainly
separated from the pack. That condition
is a combination of an immunotherapy and
ascorbic acid. Not only that, survival
was also enhanced in this combination.
Now, beyond that, when vitamin C and
immunotherapy combination are injected
directly into the lung, directly at the
site of the tumor, tumor growth is
almost completely halted. So, this means
that ascorbic acid is effective in
combating these LKB1-deficient lung
cancers when paired with anti-cancer
therapies like immunotherapies. So, now
that we know ascorbic acid can have
anti-cancerous effects, why did it get
dismissed in the past, and what new
clinical evidence exists now that would
change that narrative? The answer is
actually a mixture of what we already
went over and what previous research
didn't do.
Like I mentioned, in the late '70s and
'80s, human trials did assess efficacy
of ascorbic acid, but none of them
showed effectiveness against cancer. And
even now, the year of this recording,
there's been trials indicating no
effectiveness. So, then, why oh why are
we talking about it right now?
There's actually two reasons.
One, there's considerable uncertainty in
the ineffectiveness of vitamin C, and
two, there's a signals that it actually
may work.
So, I'm calling this uncertainty in no
effect, because while several trials
have tried and failed to show an effect
of vitamin C, the reality is that there
are two problems with the studies that
show ineffectiveness.
One, early studies did not use vitamin C
in conjunction with regular cancer
therapies, and they even relied on oral
vitamin C as opposed to intravenous. And
as we saw from the study showing vitamin
C stresses certain lung cancers, when
applying this in an animal model of
cancer, the effectiveness was really
only present when a combination
treatment was used.
Two, even the more recent trials that do
include sanction cancer therapies and
use intravenous vitamin C acknowledge
that there are several variables to
consider, like ascorbic acid, vitamin C
dosing, frequency, amount, duration, and
more. Plus, most of these studies are
safety trials, so they're not designed
to answer the question of does vitamin C
help fight cancer directly? The takeaway
here is that
there's many gaps in the evidence that
need to be filled before we can
officially shut the door on vitamin C.
So, therein lies the uncertainty.
There's plenty of room for something to
emerge, and in fact, something is
already beginning to emerge, which leads
us to my second point, the signals that
something might be there. Now, before I
dive into that, in this initial study
that we went over,
there's more to be said on exactly how
vitamin C kills cancer cells. In fact,
it's a lot like the story of the Trojan
horse of Troy, and it unravels into an
unpleasant and especially remarkable way
that cancer cells die, which leads to a
unique long-term immunity. If you're
interested in learning all those
intricacies, you can find that out in
the Physio Insider membership, which
includes extended full versions of all
my work, accompanying articles,
podcasts, live sessions, and more. It
can also be delivered to your email for
your convenience. But, you'd be missing
out on the great community that we've
built together. Now, the choice is
yours. Anyway, more science, more
takeaways, full access to everything as
an insider. The link to join is in the
description box.
In this study, which was put together
for people with colorectal cancer that
could not be removed surgically, they
randomly placed one group on a standard
anti-cancer treatment, and the other
group, the intervention group, was given
the exact same therapy,
but in addition was supplied with
intravenous vitamin C. Then, over
several years, the researchers assessed
cancer progression. They determined that
vitamin C was ineffective.
I bet you didn't expect that, did you?
But, it isn't more of the same, because
this is actually an expected outcome,
knowing what we now know. Remember, I
mentioned that the answer is in what we
went over earlier. Vitamin C was only
effective in certain cancers. In that
study, vitamin C was effective against
LKB1-deficient
cancer cells, but
was not effective, even in in the
combination with the immunotherapy, for
LKB1-sufficient
cancer cells.
That means that there's some defining
feature that needs to be present for
vitamin C to have an effect against
cancer.
So, returning to the clinical trial,
when breaking up the total group of
people with colorectal cancer based on a
specific feature called a RAS mutation,
a different story emerges. Here, we're
looking at progression-free survival, so
the higher up the lines remain, the
better. The horizontal axis is time, so
over many months, and if these people
had a tumor growth, death, or anything
else, that would dip the line down, as
they would no longer be
progression-free. The red line is the
vitamin C condition. The blue is those
that were not given high-dose vitamin C.
So, yes, here we see that vitamin C is
actually effective in humans, but it
doesn't end there.
The treatment protocol for vitamin C was
only 12 cycles, which is about 5 and 1/2
months. So, if I put the graph back up,
that means that the vitamin C aspect of
the treatment was stopped very early in
the data collection. Could the effect be
stronger, more protective if it had
lasted several years or the entire time?
We don't know, but what we do know is
that vitamin C can be effective. The
takeaway here is that vitamin C seems
ineffective when looking at cancers
across the board, but when focusing on
specific cancers, there is some evidence
that vitamin C is effective in combating
cancer. So, where does that leave us?
How should we be thinking about all this
information together?
Well, for one, we know that vitamin C
stresses and kills certain cancer cells
through increased production of these
damaging molecules within the cancer
cells. Two, intravenous vitamin C seems,
up to now, to only be clinically
effective if it's in conjunction
conjunction
with standard cancer therapies. Three,
not all cancers respond to vitamin C. It
matters which type. As for the types
that we just identified as being
affected, so RAS colorectal cancers and
LKB1-deficient lung cancers are prime
suspects, but there certainly might be
more.
Four, because of all the three previous
points, we need much more research to
tease out these details. Luckily, there
is something that you can pair with
vitamin C that indicates a potent
combination effect, and guess what?
It isn't a drug or a pharmaceutical
therapy, it's a simple nutrition
protocol. I detail everything right
here.
Thanks for tuning in. I hope this was as
fascinating for you as it was for me.
Dr. Pauling may have been onto
something, it just needed some
refinement. I'll see you in the next
one. Bye.